{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "19th century scholar Franz Mone [[MOH-nuh]] suggested the site of this battle was also the place where the hero of the Song of the Nibelung, Sigurd, slew the dragon Fafnir. Following this battle, a chieftain of the Cherusci [[keh-ROO-skee]] sent the head of his opponent to the Marcomanni to secure an alliance. At Kalkriese Hill, Germanic chieftain Arminius ambushed the forces of Varus, beginning this battle. Emperor Augustus cried \"Give me back my Legions\" following, for ten points, which devastating Roman defeat in the first century?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Teutoburg Forest or die Schlacht im Teutoburger Wald",
        "prompt on the \"Varian Disaster\" before \"Varus\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Cataldo Mission, constructed by the Jesuit missionary Pierre-Jean De Smet, is the oldest building in this U.S. state. In 1905, Frank Steunenberg [[stew-NEHN-burg]], former governor of this state, was assassinated by a disgruntled member of the Western Federation of Miners. In 1992, this state was the site of a standoff between the government and white separatist Randy Weaver at the Ruby Ridge compound, situated near this state's Canadian and Washington border. For ten points, name this state which, during the Civil War, saw a chaotic transfer of its capital from Lewiston to Boise.",
      "answer": "Idaho"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country secured its independence in the aftermath of Operation Storm, which included the retaking of Knin and the expulsion of many Orthodox Christians from Krajina [[krah-YEE-nah]]. During World War Two, a Nazi puppet state in this country was dominated by the Ustaše [[ooh-STAH-sheh]]. This country sought independence from Hungary and unification of its \"Triune Kingdom\" which included Slavonia and the coastal Kingdom of Dalmatia. For ten points, name this former Habsburg territory and constituent country of Yugoslavia, governed from Zagreb.",
      "answer": "Republic of Croatia or Republika Hrvatska"
    },
    {
      "question": "Russian lieutenant Adam Laxman landed on this island to forcibly return a pair of castaways. Shakushain’s revolt on this island was put down by the Matsumae clan, which was tasked with defending part of it. This island was the location of a short-lived separatist state called the Republic of Ezo, which opposed the Meiji government. In the closing weeks of World War Two, the city of Muroran was bombarded by American ships off the coast of, for ten points, what Japanese island, governed from Sapporo?",
      "answer": [
        "Hokkaido",
        "Ezo before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The lack of convictions surrounding this figure's death led to its site being dubbed \"The Freestate of Tallahatchie\" by the Chicago Defender. Married white woman Carolyn Bryant likely lied that this Black teenager whistled at her. This figure names a 2008 \"Act\" sponsored by John Lewis which aimed to attempt to solve cold cases of violence against Black victims prior to the 1970s. A mid-1950s mob in Mississippi murdered, for ten points, which 14 year old Black teen, whose death galvanized the Civil Rights movement?",
      "answer": "Emmett Till or Emmett Louis Till"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Karsakpay inscription describes how this leader led an army of 200,000 men to subjugate the khan of the Golden Horde, Tokhtamysh [[tohk-tah-MEESH]]. This man captured Ottoman sultan Bayezid the Thunderbolt during the Battle of Ankara. This Turko-Mongolic leader was the direct ancestor of all the Mughal emperors. For ten points, name this conqueror whose name reflects the serious injuries he suffered early in life and who established his capital at Samarkand.",
      "answer": [
        "Tamerlane",
        "Timur the Lame,",
        "Amir Timur",
        "or Timūr Gurkānī"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This tribe negotiated with Maryland Loyalist leader William Bowles, who successfully convinced them to reinforce the British fort in Pensacola during the Revolutionary War. The Seminole were originally from this non-Florida tribe, who migrated to Florida in the 18th century and mixed with local tribes like the Calusa. The militant faction of this tribe, the Red Sticks, were defeated by Andrew Jackson at Horseshoe Bend. For ten points, name this member of the \"Five Civilized Tribes\" of the Southeastern U.S., also known as the Muscogee.",
      "answer": [
        "Creek",
        "Muscogee before mentioned",
        "Red Stick Creek before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This site's monk's cell had a Buddhist style stupa added over a thousand years after its abandonment by inhabitants of the Sindhu Kingdom. A layer of bitumen coated this city's \"Great Bath,\" the earliest public water tank in recorded human history, likely used for religious purposes due to its proximity to the \"College of Priests.\" One of the largest sites of the Harappan Civilization was, for ten points, which city in modern Pakistan whose name translates to \"Mound of the Dead\"?",
      "answer": "Mohenjo-Daro"
    },
    {
      "question": "Five miles outside of this city, the first major Protestant victory of the Thirty Years' War occurred at the Battle of Breitenfeld by troops led by Gustavus Adolphus. Nazi Germany modified this city's name to reference a \"Trade Fair\" which ran unimpeded here since medieval times. The dissolution of the Confederation of the Rhine followed Napoleon's defeat at an 1813 battle named for this city, the largest fought during the 19th century. The Monument to the Battle of the Nations is in, for ten points, which city in Saxony, sixty miles from Dresden?",
      "answer": [
        "Leipzig",
        "Reichsmessestadt Leipzig",
        "Battle of Leipzig"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Bernard de Montfaucon [[mont-foh-KOHN]] brought this artwork to the attention of of Europe when he hired Antoine Benoit [[beh-NWAH]] to copy it in its entirety. This artwork, which includes an early depiction of Halley's Comet, depicts Count Guy of Ponthieu [[pohn- TOO]] holding an English king captive for ransom. During the early days of the French Revolution, this artwork was seized by the Directory to be used to cover the tops of military wagons. Harold Godwinson is shown taking an arrow in the eye in, for ten points, which medieval \"Tapestry\" depicting the Battle of Hastings?",
      "answer": "Bayeaux ] Tapestry"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Fengtian clique of warlord Zhang Zuolin [[JANG ZHUO-LIN]] was based in this region. The Willow Palisade blocked Han migration into this region. The Lytton Report was produced after the Kwantung Army invaded this region after officers staged the demolition of a section of railroad track in the Mukden Incident. Emperor Puyi was made a ruler of a Japanese puppet state in this region afterwards. For ten points, name this northeastern region of China held by Japan immediately prior to World War Two.",
        "answer": [
          "Manchuria",
          "Dōngběi",
          "Manchukuo,"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Kwantung Army was originally named for its role guarding which naval base in southern Manchuria? A sneak attack at the beginning of the Russo-Japanese War destroyed most of the Russian Pacific Fleet here.",
        "answer": [
          "Port Arthur",
          "Lüshunkou District",
          "or Lushun City",
          "Ryojun",
          "prompt on Dalian"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A vote on impeaching this governor devolved into the Bloody Monday brawl. This governor recruited prison labor to completely destroy the governor's mansion in order to build a replica of the White House in its place. This man advocated caps on income, inheritance, and net worth in his \"Share Our Wealth\" plan as a U.S. senator, three years before his assassination by Carl Weiss. For ten points, name this \"Kingfish\" who exercised near- dictatorial control over Louisiana from 1929 to 1935.",
        "answer": "Huey Long or Huey Pierce Long Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Long's death and subsequent replacement as presumptive nominee by the uncharismatic William Lemke took the wind out of what third party's attempt to capture the presidency in 1936? It was led, in part, by Father Charles Coughlin.",
        "answer": "Union Party"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A whirlpool off the coast of this country legendarily devoured a boat secured by hemp, wool, and hair ropes during a visit from king Breacan. A 1950s hysteria in this country over \"Jenny with the Iron Teeth\" and the \"Gorbals Vampire\" were traced back to American comic books. This country's folklore includes murderous water horses called \"kelpies\" and seals transformed into human women called \"selkies.\" For ten points, name this country where a dinosaur-like cryptid is said to live in Loch Ness.",
        "answer": "Scotland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Irish hero Finn MacCool legendarily built what series of submerged interlocking basalt pillars connecting Ireland's County Antrim to the coast of Scotland?",
        "answer": "Giant's Causeway"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this man broke with other Southern congressmen to oppose the Clayton Compromise, he was stabbed during a fight with state supreme court justice Francis Cone at an Atlanta hotel in 1848. This \"sage of Liberty Hall\" spent most of the Civil War writing both anonymous and signed letters denouncing Jefferson Davis's policy of conscription before leading the Confederate delegation at the Hampton Roads peace conference. For ten points, name this vice-president of the Confederacy.",
        "answer": "Alexander Stephens or Alexander Hamilton Stephens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In this March 1861 speech, Stephens used the metaphor of a building block to explain that slavery was the foundational idea of the Confederacy.",
        "answer": "Cornerstone speech"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An early one of these events on Shrove Tuesday began when white-gowned acolytes carrying red crosses claimed to “extirpate the abusive, perverse customs of Carnival.” These gatherings were often hosted in front of the Palazzo Vecchio, with an image of the devil adorned on top of a pile of straw. Sandro Botticelli legendarily threw his own artwork into the flames during these anti-pagan rituals. The Friar Girolamo Savonarola led, for ten points, which mass burnings of supposedly obscene art in 15th century Florence?",
        "answer": [
          "Bonfire of the Vanities",
          "falò delle vanità"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Savonarola's followers were known as the Piagnoni which referred to what action they took, usually to lament the sins of the world?",
        "answer": [
          "Weeping or Weepers",
          "Crying",
          "synonyms",
          "Whine",
          "NOTE: \"Piagnoni\" translates to either \"Weepers\"",
          "\"Whiners\""
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The 1st Earl of Shaftesbury likely manufactured charges of Catholic sympathies against this Admiralty Secretary, leading to his imprisonment in the Tower of London. This man, who was a member of the entourage of Charles II on his return from the Netherlands during the Restoration, recorded the destruction of St. Paul's Cathedral during a blaze which began on Pudding Lane. The 17th century Great Plague and Great Fire of London were chronicled by, for ten points, which former minister of Parliament who kept a diary that was published to popular acclaim in the 19th century?",
        "answer": "Samuel Pepys ]"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pepys recorded his participation in the navy during which war's Raid of the Medway? England attempted to end a namesake rival's naval domination in the North Sea and English Channel in this war.",
        "answer": "Second Anglo-Dutch War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A biography accused this author of plagiarizing Emma Langdon Roche in a 1928 article recapping an interview with slave trade survivor Cudjoe Lewis. This author depicted the Southern practice of \"paramour rights\" in her 1934 novel Jonah's Gourd Vine. This author extensively collected Caribbean and southern folklore in books such as Tell My Horse and Mules and Men. For ten points, name this author of a 1937 novel about the Black town of Eatonville, Florida, Their Eyes Were Watching God.",
        "answer": "Zora Neale Hurston"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hurston's 1948 novel about Jim Meserve's pursuit of Arvay Henson is titled for a Seraph on what river, which also appears in the first line of the Florida state song, \"Old Folks at Home\"? Arising in the Okefenokee Swamp, it hosted many Timucua settlements.",
        "answer": "Suwanee River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, Sébastien Rale [[RAH-leh]] had a price put on his head by Massachusetts governor Joseph Dudley, who wrongly assumed he had led a raid in Maine. The expulsion of residents who were later dubbed \"Cajuns\" occurred during this war's American theater, known as \"Queen Anne's War.\" The death of the childless Charles II, a member of the Habsburg family, led to this multi-continental war. The Treaty of Utrecht ended, for ten points, what early 18th century war which led to the rise of the Bourbon monarchy in Iberia?",
        "answer": [
          "War of the Spanish Succession",
          "Queen Anne's War before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the European theatre of the war, the Duke of Marlborough was partnered with which French-born Austrian general who secured a major victory in the Siege of Turin?",
        "answer": "Eugene of Savoy or Prince Eugene Francis of Savoy–Carignano"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Adlai Stevenson",
      "prompt": "Concerning Adlai Stevenson II, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Republican president of the 1950s and early 60s who defeated Stevenson twice in back to back landslide victories.",
          "answer": "Dwight David Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Midwestern state which Stevenson governed.",
          "answer": "Illinois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future Attorney General and victim of Sirhan Sirhan who served as an aide for Stevenson on the 1956 presidential campaign.",
          "answer": "Robert Fitzgerald Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempted overthrow of the Castro regime by Cuban exiles which nearly led to Adlai Stevenson resigning as Ambassador to the UN.",
          "answer": [
            "Bay of Pigs Incident",
            "Playa Giron"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-communist period pushed by Joseph McCarthy that coincided with Stevenson's stint as governor.",
          "answer": "Second Red Scare"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. government official who was accused of Communism and spying by Whittaker Chambers and who was defended by Stevenson in a private deposition.",
          "answer": "Alger Hiss"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennessee politician who served as Stevenson's running mate in the 1956 election.",
          "answer": "Carey Estes Kefauver"
        },
        {
          "question": "Derisive nickname of Stevenson later embraced by him on the 1952 campaign trail which poked fun at his baldness and intellectual air.",
          "answer": "Egghead"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nikita Khrushchev",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Soviet First Secretary of the 1950s and 1960s, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Present-day nation where, until the fall of Kiev to the Germans, Khrushchev headed the Communist Party.",
          "answer": "Ukraine or Ukraïna"
        },
        {
          "question": "World War Two battle on the Volga river which Khrushchev participated in under Georgy Zhukov.",
          "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crisis concerning the placement of ballistic missiles on a Caribbean nation by the Khrushchev regime.",
          "answer": "Cuban Missile Crisis"
        },
        {
          "question": "First artificial satellite launched by the Soviet space program in 1957.",
          "answer": "Sputnik 1"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oration given by Khrushchev to denounce his predecessor, Joseph Stalin.",
          "answer": [
            "Secret Speech or Sekretnïy Doklad",
            "\"On the Cult of Personality and Its Consequences\"",
            "or O kul'te lichnosti i yego posledstviyakh"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Debate\" between Vice President Nixon and Khrushchev at the American National Exhibition.",
          "answer": [
            "Kitchen Debate",
            "Kukhonnye debaty"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Favorite of Stalin who immediately succeeded him before being politically outmaneuvered by Khrushchev.",
          "answer": "Georgy Malenkov or Georgy Maximilianovich Malenkov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Communist Romania who resisted Khrushchev's program of of de- Stalinization.",
          "answer": "Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej ]"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Berber People",
      "prompt": "Concerning the history of the Berbers, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Catholic Church father of Berber origin who wrote Confessions and City of God.",
          "answer": "St. Augustine of Hippo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phoenician city-state in North Africa which used Berber horsemen as mercenaries.",
          "answer": [
            "Carthage",
            "Carthago"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Arab caliphate that succeeded the Rashidun and conquered the Berbers in the 8th century.",
          "answer": "Umayyad Caliphate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Berber scholar of the 14th century who departed from Morocco for the hajj and became the most traveled explorer in history prior to the Industrial Revolution.",
          "answer": "Ibn Battuta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Berber kingdom and rival of Rome led by Kings Jugurtha and Massinissa.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Numidia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medieval Berber caliphate that overthrew the Almoravids and controlled both the Maghreb and Andalusia.",
          "answer": "Almohad Caliphate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern Saharan nation which shares its name with a Berber kingdom that served as a client state to Rome.",
          "answer": "Mauretania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Berber writer of The Golden Ass, the only novel to survive in its entirety from the Roman period.",
          "answer": "Apuleius or Lucius Apuleius Madaurensis"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman’s feud with doctors during the U.S. Civil War prompted the War Department to introduce Order No. 351 in October 1863. That order allowed this woman, in her capacity as the Superintendent of (20 pts)",
        "Army Nurses, to appoint female nurses. Prior to this woman’s appointment by the Union Army, this woman penned a bill vetoed by Franklin Pierce to set aside ten million acres to be used for the benefit of the “blind, (10 pts)",
        "deaf, and dumb.” For ten points, name this social advocate who created the first generation of U.S. mental asylums."
      ],
      "answer": "Dorothea Dix or Dorothea Lynde Dix"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "In this non-African city, over 80 people were injured after the execution of Congolese prime minister Patrice Lumumba motivated its population to storm the Belgian embassy. Suleiman the Magnificent mass-deported this city's (*) Orthodox population to Istanbul and made it the center of the Sanjak of Smederevo. Over 100,000 people took to the streets of this city to protest the genocidal regime of Slobodan (*) Milošević [[mih-LOH-seh-vitch]] in the mid-1990s. For ten points, name this Danubian \"White City\" and former capital of united Yugoslavia, now the capital of independent Serbia."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Belgrade",
        "Belgrad",
        "Dar Al Jihad"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A note supposedly written by the subject of this event was found in the wastebasket of Prussian attaché Maximilian von Schwartzkoppen, only for that German officer to later reveal he was in contact with Ferdinand (20 pts)",
        "Esterhazy. Following this affair, future prime minister Leon Blum participated in the defense of Emile Zola after he was brought to court for criticizing this treason trial in his pamphlet (10 pts)",
        "J'Accuse. For ten points, name this anti-Semitic \"Affair\" during the French Third Republic caused by the false prosecution of a Jewish artillery officer."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dreyfus Affair",
        "l'affaire Dreyfus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "It's not a feast, but the Gaelic festival of Lughnasadh [[loo-nah-SAHD]] traditionally begins with this specific event to commemorate the mother-goddess Tailte. While held in veneration for Zeus in Classical Greece, scholars speculate the (*) Olympics first began as one of these events during its Dark Ages. Aeneas hosts one of these events in book 5 of the Aeneid to honor his father Anchises [[ahn-KYE-sees]], who fell during the escape from Troy. In the Iliad, events like chariot-racing and (*) wrestling occur during, for ten points, what type of event held after the death of Patroclus?"
      ],
      "answer": "Funeral Games"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure, who said \"When the rich think about the poor, they have poor ideas,\" replaced the Sociedad de Beneficencia with her own namesake foundation. The Montoneros (20 pts)",
        "kidnapped the body of Pedro Eugenio Aramburu in an effort to repatriate this figure's corpse back to her home nation from Spain. This first Argentinian to receive chemotherapy was initially nominated as the vice-presidential candidate for her (10 pts)",
        "spouse in the 1952 elections. For ten points, name this actress turned First Lady of Argentina during the mid 20th century known affectionally as \"Evita.\""
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Eva Perón or María Eva Duarte de Perón",
        "Evita Perón"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The salutation of the sun by Syrian soldiers under this general was misinterpreted by the enemy army led by Vitellian as incoming reinforcements, causing them to break at the Second Battle of Bedriacum. The supposed descendant of Julius Caesar, Gaius Julius Civilis, rose in rebellion against this leader during the (20 pts)",
        "Batavian Rebellion. This emperor, who deployed the general Agricola to Britain, also ordered the construction of the (10 pts)",
        "Coliseum. The victor of the Year of Four Emperors was, for ten points, which Roman Emperor and founder of the Flavian dynasty?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Vespasian or Vespasianus",
        "Titus Flavius Vespasianus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The primary attorney of the defendent in this case, Thomas Addis Emmet, previously served as barrister for the revolutionary Society of the United Irishmen. In this case, Attorney General William (20 pts)",
        "Wirt argued that the federal patent preemptively applied for by the plaintiff superseded any regulation from the state. Congress's right to regulate interstate (10 pts)",
        "commerce was upheld in this 19th century court case. The monopoly of Robert Fulton on New York waters was deemed unconstitutional in, for ten points, which 1824 Supreme Court case?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gibbons v. Ogden",
        "either"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A month after this work’s premiere, it was re-scored for a performance at Foundling Hospital. Due to the Duke of Montagu’s insistence on the omission of non- martial instruments, this piece's composer was forced to remove the intended (20 pts)",
        "string parts. Thomas Desaguliers [[duh-sah-gool-YEH]], who was elected to the Royal Society for his artillery research, was fire master at this work's premiere. The signing of a treaty in Aachen is commemorated in this piece, which was commissioned to celebrate the end of the War of the (10 pts)",
        "Austrian Succession. For ten points, name this monarch-approved suite by George Frideric Handel."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Music for the Royal Fireworks",
        "Royal Fireworks Music"
      ]
    }
  ]
}